<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections on a pamphlet entitled Parliamentum pacificum</title>
            <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28839</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10836118</idno>
  <idno type="VID">46081</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248515353</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R694A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29160</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10836118</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28839)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46081)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1418:11b or 1642:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections on a pamphlet entitled Parliamentum pacificum</title>
                  <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
                  <author>Northleigh, John, 1657-1705. Parliamentum pacificum, or, The happy union of king &amp; people in an healing Parlament heartily wish't for, and humbly recommended.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed by the Earl of Sutherland, and printed at London in March, 1688" [i.e. 1689].</note>
                  <note>Item appears at reel 1418:11 and 1642:17.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: Pages stained, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
                  <note>Item at 1418:11b is bound with: Dr. Burnets vindication of himself from the calumnies with which he is aspersed in a pamphlet entitled Parliamentum pacificum.  [Amsterdam? : s.n., 1688?].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Parliamentum pacificum.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:46081:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46081:1"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS On A PAMPHLET, Entitled, PARLIAMENTUM PACIFICUM.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>Licensed</hi> by the Earl of <hi>Sunderland,</hi> and printed at <hi>London</hi> in March, 1688.</head>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>PEace</hi> is a very desirable thing, yet every State that is <hi>peaceable</hi> is not blindly to be courted. An Apoplexy is the most <hi>pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable</hi> State, in which a mans Body can be laid: yet few would desire to pacify the humours of their Body at that rate. An <hi>Implicite Faith</hi> and <hi>Absolute Slavery</hi> are the two peaceablest things that can be; yet we confess, we have no mind to try so dangerous an Experiment: and while the Remedies are too strong, we will choose rather to bear our Disease, than to venture on them. The Instance that is proposed, to the Imitation of the Nation, is, that <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> which called in the late <hi>King:</hi> and yet that cannot so much as be called a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> unless it be upon a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth Principle, that <hi>the Soveraign Power is radically in the People:</hi> for its being chosen without the <hi>Kings Writ,</hi> was such an <hi>Essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Nullity,</hi> that no subsequent Ratification could take it away: for all People saw, that they could not depend upon any <hi>Acts</hi> passed by it: and therefore it was quickly dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: and ever since it has been called by all the Monarchical Party, A <hi>Convention,</hi> and not a <hi>Parliament.</hi> But now in order to the Courting the Commonwealth Party, this is not only called a <hi>Parliament,</hi> but is proposed as a Pattern to all others, from the beginning to Page 19.</p>
            <p n="2">II. But since this Author will send us back to that time, &amp; since he takes it so ill that <hi>the Memory of the late King should be forgotten.</hi> Let us examin that Transaction a little, and then we shall see whether it had not been more for his <hi>Honour</hi> to let it be <hi>forgotten.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> did indeed in his <hi>Declaration</hi> from <hi>Breda</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> on which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted in a large and wise <hi>Declaration,</hi> set out after he was setled on the Throne: but after that he had got a <hi>Parliament,</hi> chosen all of Creatures depending on himself, who for many years granted him every thing that he desired, a severe <hi>Act of Uniformity</hi> was passed: and the Kings Promise was carried off by this, <hi>that the King could not refuse to comply with so loyal a Parliament.</hi> It is well enough known, that those who were then secretly <hi>Papists,</hi> and who disguised their Religion for many years after this, as the <hi>King</hi> himself did to the last, animated the <hi>Chief-men</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> to carry the points of <hi>Uniformity</hi> as high as was possible; and that both then, and ever since, all that proposed any expedients for uniting us (or as it was afterwards termed, for <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the Dissenters</hi>) were represented as <hi>the Betrayers of the Church.</hi> The Design was then clear to some; that so by carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Terms of <hi>Conformity</hi> to a great rigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, there might be many <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> and great occasion given for a <hi>Toleration,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:46081:2"/>under which Popery might insensibly creep in: for if the Expedients that the <hi>King</hi> himself proposed in his <hi>Declaration,</hi> had been stood to, it is well known, that of the 2000. Conscientious <hi>Ministers,</hi> as he calls them pag. 14 by an Affectation too gross to pass on them, that were turned out, above 1700. had staid in. Their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices had but too good success on those who were then at the Head of our <hi>Church:</hi> whose Spirits were too much soured by their ill usage during the War, and whose Principles led them to so good an opinion of all that the <hi>Court</hi> did, that for a great while they would suspect nothing. But at the same time that the <hi>Church Party,</hi> that carried all before them in that <hi>Parliament,</hi> were animated to press things so hard, the <hi>Dissenters</hi> were secretly encouraged to stand out: and were told, that the <hi>King's</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Principle, and the Consideration of <hi>Trade</hi> would certainly procure them a <hi>Toleration:</hi> and ever since, that Party that thus had set us together by the ears, has shifted sides dextrously enough; but still they have carried on the main De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, which was to keep up the Quarrel in the Intervals of Parliament, <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> was in vogue; but when a <hi>Session of Parliament</hi> came, and the <hi>King</hi> wanted Money, then a new severe Law against the <hi>Dissenters</hi> was offered to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry men of the <hi>Church Party,</hi> as the price of it; and this seldom failed to have its effect: so that they were like the <hi>Jewels of the Crown,</hi> pawned when the <hi>King</hi> needed Money, but redeemed at the next Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. A Reflection then that arises na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally out of the proceedings in the year 1660. is, that if a <hi>Parliament</hi> should come, that would copy after that pattern, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests:</hi> The Kings offers of <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> as may indeed be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, will bind him till after a short Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion or two such a meritorious <hi>Parliament</hi> should be dissolved, according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent in the year 1660. and that a new one were brought together by the same Methods of changing Charters and making returns, and then the Old Laws <hi>de Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co comburendo</hi> might be again revived, and it would be said, that the King's Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are for keeping his Promise and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting still a Liberty of Conscience, yet he can deny nothing to a Loyal and Catholick <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. We pay all possible respect to the <hi>King;</hi> and have witnessed how much we depended on his Promises, in so signal a manner, that after such real Evidence all words are superfluous. But since the <hi>King</hi> has shewed so much zeal, not only for his <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligion</hi> in general, but in particular for that <hi>Society,</hi> which of all the other Bodies in it, we know is animated the most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us, we must crave leave to speak a little freely, and not suffer our selves to be destroyed by a Complement. The <hi>Extirpation of Hereticks,</hi> and the <hi>Breach of Faith to them,</hi> have been decreed by two of their General Councils, and by a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of several Ages; the <hi>Pape</hi> is possessed of a <hi>Power of dissolving all Promises, Contracts and Oaths;</hi> not to mention the private Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of that <hi>Society,</hi> that is so much in favour, of <hi>doing ill that good may come of it, of using Equivocations and Reservations, and of ordering the Intention.</hi> Now these Opinions as they have never been renounced by the Body of that <hi>Church,</hi> so indeed they cannot be, unless they renounce their Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which is their <hi>Basis,</hi> at the same time. Therefore tho a Prince of that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, may very sincerely resolve to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> and to <hi>keep his word,</hi> yet the blind Subjection into which he is brought by his Religion, to his Church, must force him to break thro all that, as soon as the Doctrine of his Church is opened to him; and that Absolution is denied him, or higher Threatnings are made him; if he continues firm to his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Inclinations. So that supposing His Majesties Piety to be as <hi>great</hi> as the <hi>Iesuites</hi> Sermon, on the 30. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> lately prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, carries it, to <hi>the uttermost possibility of Flesh and Blood,</hi> then our Fears must still grow upon us, who know what are the Decrees of that <hi>Church;</hi> and by consequence we may infer to what his Piety must needs
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46081:2"/>carry him: as soon as those things are fully opened to him, which in <hi>respect to him,</hi> we are bound to believe are now hid from him.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. It will further appear, that these are not injust Inferences: if we consider a little what has been the Observation of all the Promises made for <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> to Hereticks by <hi>R. Catholick Princes,</hi> ever since the <hi>Reformation.</hi> The first was, the <hi>Edict of Passaw</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> procured chiefly by <hi>Ferdinands</hi> means, and maintained indeed Religiously by his Son <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, whose Inclinations to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion made him be suspected for one himself: but the <hi>Iesuites</hi> insinuated themselves so far into his younger <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Court, that was Archduke of <hi>Grats,</hi> that this was not only broken by that Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in their Share, but tho <hi>Rodolph</hi> and <hi>Mathias</hi> were Princes of great Gentleness, and the latter of these, was the Protector of the <hi>States</hi> in the beginning of their War with King <hi>Philip</hi> the Second, yet the violence with which the House of <hi>Grats</hi> was possessed, overturned all that: so that the breaking of the Pacificatory <hi>Edicts</hi> was begun in <hi>Rodolph's</hi> time, and was so far car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on in <hi>Mathias</hi>'s time, that they set both <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary</hi> in a Flame; and so begun that long War of <hi>Germany.</hi> 2. The next Promise for <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> was made by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but we know well enough how it was observed: the Promises made by the Queen <hi>Regent</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> were observed with the same Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity: after these came the Pacificatory <hi>Edicts</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> which were scarce made when the <hi>Triumvirate</hi> was formed to break them. The famous <hi>Massacre of Paris</hi> was an Instance never to be forgot of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Observance of a Treaty, made on Purpose to say the Party asleep, and to bring the whole Heads of it into the Net, this was a much more <hi>dreadful St. Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi> than that on which our Author be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stows that Epithete pag. 15. and when all seemed setled by the famous <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Nantes,</hi> we have seen how restless that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in particular the <hi>Society,</hi> were till it was broken; by a Prince, that for thirty years together had shewed as great an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to the <hi>Shedding of Blood,</hi> in his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at home, as any of his Neighbours can pretend to: &amp; who has done nothing in the whole Tragedy that he has acted, but what is exactly conform to the Doctrine &amp; Decrees of his Church: so that it is not <hi>himself,</hi> but <hi>his Religion,</hi> that we must blame for all that has fallen out in that Kingdom. I cannot leave this without taking notice of our Author's Sincerity, who page 18. tells us of the <hi>Protestants entring into their League in France,</hi> when it is well known that it was a <hi>League of Papists against a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Successor,</hi> which was afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to a <hi>Popish King,</hi> only because he was not zealous enough against <hi>Hereticks.</hi> But to end this List of Instances at a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to which our Author bears so particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar a kindness; when the Dutchess of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> granted the <hi>Edict</hi> of Pacification, by which all that was past, was buried; and the Exercise of the Protestant Religion was to be connived at for the future: King <hi>Philip</hi> the Second did not only ratify this, but expressed himself so fully upon it to the Count of <hi>Egmont,</hi> who had been sent over to him, that the easy <hi>Count</hi> returned to <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> so assured of the <hi>King</hi>'s Sincerity, that he endeavoured to perswade all others to rely as much on his word, as he himself did. It is well known how fatal this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence was to him: and (see <hi>Meteren</hi> lib. 3.) that two years after this that <hi>King</hi> sent over the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> with that severe Commission, which has been often printed: in which, without any regard had to the former Pacification or Promises, the <hi>King</hi> declared, <hi>that the Provinces had forfeited all their Liberties, and that every man in it had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited his life:</hi> and therefore he authorised that <hi>unmerciful man</hi> to proceed with all pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible rigor against them. It is also remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, that that bloody Commission is founded on the King's <hi>Absolute Power,</hi> and his zeal for Religion. This is the only <hi>Edict</hi> that I know, in which a <hi>King</hi> has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to <hi>Absolute Power,</hi> before the <hi>two Declarations</hi> for <hi>Scotland</hi> in the year 1687.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46081:3"/>so whether they who penned them, took their pattern from this, I cannot deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min it. I could carry this view of History much further, to shew in many more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, how little <hi>Protestants</hi> can depend on the Faith of <hi>Ro. Catholicks:</hi> and that their condition is so much the worse, the more pious that their Princes are. As for what may be objected to all this, from the present State of some Principalities or Towns in <hi>Germany,</hi> or of the <hi>Switsers</hi> and <hi>Grisons;</hi> it is to be considered, that in some of these want of power in the <hi>Ro. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> to do mischief, and the other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of their affairs, are visibly the only Securities of the <hi>Protestants:</hi> and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever this Nation departs from that, and gives up the <hi>Laws,</hi> it is no hard thing to guess how short-lived the <hi>Liberty of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> even tho setled into a <hi>Magna Charta</hi> would be.</p>
            <p n="5">V. All that our Author says upon the General Subject of <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> is only a severe Libel upon that <hi>Church,</hi> whose principles and practices are so contrary to it. But the Proposition lately made, has put an end to all this dispute; since by an Offer of Repealing the <hi>Penal Lawes,</hi> res<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only those of the <hi>Test,</hi> and such others as secure the <hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion is now no more, which Religion must be <hi>tolerated,</hi> but which Religion must <hi>Reign</hi> and prevail. All that is here of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in opposition to that, is that by this means <hi>such a number of persons must be ruined,</hi> Page 64. <hi>which is as severe a way of forcing people to change their Religion, as the way of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agoons.</hi> I will not examin the particulars of this matter, but must express my joy to find, that all the difficulty which is in our way to a happy quiet, is the supplying such a number of men with the means of their subsistence, which by the execution of the <hi>Law</hi> for the <hi>Test,</hi> must be taken from them. This by all that I can learn, will not come to near an hundred thousand pound a year: and indeed the supplying of those of the <hi>King's</hi> Religion, that want it, is a piece of Charity and Bounty so worthy of him, that I do not know a man, that would envy them the double of this in pensions: and if such a sum would a little Charge the <hi>King's</hi> Revenue, I dare say, when the Settlement of the Nation is brought to that single point, there would not be one Negative found in either <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for the reimbursing the <hi>King:</hi> so far are we from desiring, either the Destruction, or even the poverty of those that perhaps wait only for an occasion to burn us. I will add one bold thing further, that tho I will be no undertaker, for what a <hi>Parliament</hi> may do, yet I am confident that all men are so far from any desire of Revenge, but most of all, that the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical minds</hi> of the <hi>next Successors,</hi> are above it, that if an <hi>Indemnity</hi> for that bold violation of the <hi>Law,</hi> that has been of late both practised and authorised among us, would procure a full Settlement, even this could be obtained: tho an Impunity after such Transgressions, is perhaps too great an Encouragement to offend for the future. But since it is the preservation of the Nation, and not the ruin of any party in it, that is aimed at, the Hardiness of this Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will I hope be forgiven me. It is urged pag. 63. that according to the <hi>Dutch</hi> pattern at least the <hi>Ro. Catholicks</hi> may have a Share in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Employments, but the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween our Case and theirs is clear: since some <hi>Ro. Catholick Officers,</hi> where the Government is wholly in the Hands of <hi>Protestants,</hi> cannot be of such dangerous consequence, as it must needs be under a <hi>King</hi> that is not only of that perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, but is become nearly allied to the <hi>Society</hi> as the <hi>Liege Letter</hi> tells us.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. It is true, our Author would persuade us, that the <hi>King's</hi> dispensing power has already put an end to the dispute: and that therefore it is <hi>a seeming sort of perjury,</hi> see pag. 48. <hi>to keep the Justices of peace still under an Oath of executing those Lawes,</hi> which they must consider no more. Some Presidents are brought from former times, p. 22, 23, 24. of our <hi>Kings</hi> using the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pencing power in <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d, <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d, <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th, <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, and Q. <hi>Elisabeth</hi>'s time. It is very true, that the <hi>Lawes</hi> have been of late broke through among us with a very high hand: but it is a little too dangerous to upbraid the <hi>Justices of Peace</hi> with their <hi>Oaths,</hi> lest this oblige them to reflect on so sacred an engagement: for the worthy Members of <hi>Magdalen Colledg</hi> are not the only persons in <hi>England,</hi> who will make Conscience of observing their <hi>Oaths:</hi> so that if others are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46081:3"/>brought to reflect too much on what they do, our Authors officiousness in suggesting this to them may prove to be no acceptable piece of service. I will not examin all his Presidents: we are to be Governed by <hi>Law,</hi> and not by some of the <hi>excesses of Government:</hi> nor is the Latter end of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third a time to be much imitated: and of all the parts of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> History <hi>Richard</hi> the 2ds reign should be the least mentioned: since those <hi>excesses</hi> of his produced so Tragical a Conclusion as the loss of <hi>his</hi> Crown and Life. <hi>Henry</hi> the 6ths feeble and imbroiled Reign will scarce support an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and if there were some excesses in <hi>Henry</hi> the 8ths time, which is ordinary in all great Revolutions, he got all these to be either War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted, or afterwards confirmed in <hi>Parliament.</hi> And Q. <hi>Elisabeths</hi> power in Ecclesiastical mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters was founded on a special <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> which was in a great measure repealed in the year 1641. and that Repeal was again ratified by another <hi>Act</hi> in the late <hi>Kings</hi> time. We are often told, of the late <hi>King's</hi> Repealing the <hi>Act</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the sise of <hi>Carts</hi> and <hi>Wagons:</hi> but all Lawyers know, that some <hi>Laws</hi> are understood to be <hi>Abrogated</hi> without a speciall <hi>Repeal,</hi> when some Visible Inconvenience enforces it: such as appeared in that mistaken <hi>Act</hi> concerning <hi>Wagons:</hi> so the <hi>King</hi> in that case only declared the Inconvenience which made that <hi>Law</hi> to be of it self null because it was Impracticable: It is true, the <hi>Parliament</hi> never questioned this: a man would not be offended if another pulled a flower in his garden, that yet would take it ill if he broke his hedge: and in <hi>Holland,</hi> to which our Authors pen leads him often, when a river changes its course, any man may break the <hi>Dike</hi> that was made to resist it, yet that will be no warrant to go, and break the Dike that resists the current of the same River: so if a dispencing power when applyed to smaller offences, has been passed over, as an <hi>excess of Government,</hi> that might be excusable, tho not justifiable, this will by no means prove, that <hi>Laws</hi> made to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us against that which we esteem the <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test of evils</hi> may be superceded, because <hi>twelve men</hi> in <hi>Scarlet</hi> have been hired or practised on to say so, the power of <hi>pardoning</hi> is also unreaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably urged for justifying the <hi>dispensing power;</hi> the one, is a grace to a particular person for a crime committed, whereas the other is a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to commit crimes: in short, the one is a power to <hi>save men,</hi> and the other is a power to <hi>destroy the Government.</hi> But tho they swagger it out now with the <hi>Dispensing power,</hi> yet <hi>rode caper vitem</hi> may come to be again in season: and a time may come, in which the whole party will have reason to wish that some hare-brained <hi>Jesuites</hi> had never been born, who will rather expose them not only to the Resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but even to the Justice of another sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, in which as little regard will be had to the <hi>dispencing power,</hi> as they have to the <hi>Laws</hi> at present; then accept of reasonable propositions.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Our Author's kindness to the <hi>States of Holland,</hi> is very particular, and returns often upon him; and it is no wonder that a <hi>State</hi> setled upon two such hinges, as the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> and <hi>Publick Liberty,</hi> should be no small eyesore, to those who intend to destroy both. So that the Slackning the <hi>Laws</hi> concerning <hi>Religion,</hi> and the Invading that <hi>State,</hi> seem to be Terms that must alwayes go together. In the first War began the first Slackning of them And after the <hi>Triple Alliance</hi> had laid the <hi>Dutch</hi> asleep, when the second War was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved on, which began with that Heroical Attempt on the <hi>Smirna Fleet</hi> (for our Author will not have the late <hi>Kings</hi> Actions to be <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten</hi>) at the same time the famous <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> suspending the <hi>Laws</hi> in 1672. came out: And now again with another <hi>Declaration</hi> to the same purpose, we see a return of the same good Inclinations for the <hi>Dutch,</hi> tho none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Author has ever ventured in a Book licenced by My Lord <hi>President</hi> of the <hi>Council,</hi> to call their Constitution, Page 68. <hi>A Revolt that they made from their Lawful Frince,</hi> and to raise his stile to a more sublime strain, he says P. 66. <hi>that their Commonwealth is only the result of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Rebellion, Revolt and Defection from their Trince, and that the Lawes that they have made, were to prevent any Casual return to their natural Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</hi> And speaking of their Obligation, to protect a Naturalised Subject, he bestows this Honour on them, as to say, Pag. 57, 58. <hi>Those that never yet dealt so fairly with Princes, may be suspected for such a superfluous Faith to one that puts himself upon them for a Vassal.</hi> Time will shew how far the States will resent these Injuries: only, it seems our Author thinks, that a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns Faith to protect the Subject is a <hi>super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous thing;</hi> a Faith to Hereticks is another <hi>su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous thing:</hi> so that two Suiperfluities, one upon another, must be all that we are to trust to. But I must take notice of the variety of Methods, that these Gentlemen use in their Writings. Here in <hi>England,</hi> we are always up
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46081:4"/>braided with the <hi>Revolt of the Dutch,</hi> as a scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Imputation on the <hi>Protestant Religion:</hi> and yet in a late Paper, entitled, an <hi>Answer to Pensioner Fagel's Letter,</hi> the Services that the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> did, in the beginning of that Commonwealth, are highly extolled as signal and meritorious: upon which the Writer makes great Complaints, that the <hi>Pacification of Gaunt,</hi> and the <hi>Union at Utrecht,</hi> by which the free Exercise of their Religion was to be continued to them, was not observed in most of the <hi>Provinces:</hi> But if he had taken pains to examin the History of the <hi>States;</hi> he would have found, that soon after the <hi>Union</hi> made at <hi>Utrecht,</hi> the Treaty at <hi>Collen</hi> was set on foot, between the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>States,</hi> by the <hi>Emperors</hi> Mediation, in which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> studied to divide the <hi>Ro. Catholicks</hi> of these <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> from the <hi>Protestants,</hi> by offering a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of all the other <hi>Priviledges</hi> of these <hi>Provinces,</hi> excepting only the point of <hi>Religion:</hi> which had so great an effect, that the Party of the <hi>Malcontents</hi> was formed upon it: and these did quickly Capitulate in the <hi>Walloon Provinces,</hi> and after that not only <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> Capitulated, but <hi>Reenenburgh</hi> that was Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Groening,</hi> declared for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and by some Places that he took both in <hi>Friseland</hi> and <hi>Over-Issel,</hi> he put these <hi>Provinces</hi> under Contribution: Not long after that both <hi>Deventer</hi> and <hi>Zutphen</hi> were betrayed by <hi>Popish</hi> Governours: and the War was thus brought within the <hi>seven</hi> Provinces, that had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore kept at a greater distance from them. Thus it did appear almost every where, that the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with which the <hi>Priests</hi> were inspiring the <hi>R. Catholicks</hi> against the <hi>Protestants,</hi> disposed them to betray all again to the <hi>Spanish</hi> Tyranny. The new War that <hi>Reenenburgh's</hi> Treachery had brought into these <hi>Provinces,</hi> changed so the state of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, that no wonder it this produced a change likewise with Relation to that Religion, since it appeared that these Revolts were carried on, and justified upon the Principles of that <hi>Church:</hi> and the general hatred under which these Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volts brought the <hi>Ro. Catholicks</hi> in those <hi>Out Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces,</hi> made the greater part of them to withdraw: so that there were not left such numbers of them as to pretend to the free exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of their Religion. But the War not having got into <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Utrecht:</hi> and none of that Religion having revolted in those Provinces, the <hi>Ro. Catholicks</hi> continued still in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: and tho the ill Inclination that they shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, made it necessary for the Publick Safety, to put them out of the Government, yet they have still enjoyed the common Rights of the Countrey, with the free Exercise of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. But it is plain, that some men are only wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an Opportunity to renew the old <hi>Delenda est carthago:</hi> and that they think it is no small step to it, to possess all the World with odious Impressions of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as a <hi>Rebellious and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious State:</hi> and if it were possible, they would even make their own <hi>Ro: Catholick</hi> Subjects, Fancy that they are persecuted by them: but tho men may be brought to believe <hi>Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation,</hi> in spite of the Evidence of Sense to the contrary; yet those that feel themselves at ease, will hardly be brought to think that they are persecuted, because they are told so in an ill writ <hi>Pamphlet.</hi> And for their Rebellion, the <hi>Prince</hi> that is only concerned in that, finds them now to be his <hi>best Allies</hi> and <hi>Chief Supports,</hi> as his Predecessours acknowledged them a <hi>Free State</hi> almost an Age ago. And it being confessed by the Historians of all sides, that there was an express proviso, in the Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Government, <hi>That if their Prince broke such and such Limits, they were no more bound to obey him, but might resist him;</hi> and it being no le s certain, that King <hi>Philip</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond authorised the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> to seise upon all their Priviledges, their resisting him, and maintaining their Priviledges, was without all dispute a justifiable Action: and was so esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Europe;</hi> and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar here in <hi>England,</hi> as appears by the <hi>Preambles</hi> of several <hi>Acts of Subsidy</hi> that were given the <hi>Queen</hi> in order to the assisting the <hi>States,</hi> and as for their <hi>not dealing Fairly with Princes,</hi> when our Author can find such an Instance in their History, as our attempt upon their <hi>Smirna Fleet</hi> was, he may employ his Eloquence in setting it out: and if notwithstanding all the Failures that they have felt from others, they have still maintained the Publick Faith, our Author's Rhetorick will hardly blemish them. The Peace of <hi>Nimmegen</hi> and the abandoning of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> are perhaps the single Instances in their History, that need to be a little excused. But as the vast expence of the late War brought them into a Necessity that either knows no Law, or at least will hearken to none, so we who forced them to both, and first sold the <hi>Triple Alliance,</hi> and then let go <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> do with a very ill grace, reproach the <hi>Dutch</hi> for these unhappy steps to which our Conduct drove them.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:46081:4"/> VIII. If a strain of pert boldness runs thro this whole <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> it appears no where more Eminently, than in the <hi>Reflections</hi> the Author makes on Mr. <hi>Fagel's Letter:</hi> He calls it, Page 62, a <hi>pretended Piece,</hi> and a <hi>Presumption not to be soon pardoned, in prefixing to a surreptitious and unautho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rised Pamphlet the reverend name of the Princess of Orange:</hi> which in another place (Page 72.) he had reason to imagin, was <hi>but a Counterfeit Coyn, and that those Venerable Characters were but Politically feigned, and a Sacred Title given to it without their Authority.</hi> All this coming out with so solemn a Licence, has made me take some pains to be rightly informed in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: those whom I consulted, tell me, they have discoursed the <hi>Pensioner</hi> himself on this Subject; who will very shortly take a sure Method to clear himself of those Imputations, and to do that right to the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princess,</hi> as to shew the World that in this matter he acted only by their order. For as Mr. <hi>Stewarts</hi> Letter, drew the <hi>Pensioner's</hi> Answer from him, so this Paper <hi>licensed as it is,</hi> will now draw from him a particular recital of the whole Progress of this Matter. Mr. <hi>Albeville</hi> knows, that the <hi>Princess</hi> explained herself so fully to him in the Moneth of <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June</hi> 1687. upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal of the <hi>Test,</hi> that he himself has acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to several persons, that tho both the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princess</hi> were very stiff in that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; yet of the two, he found the <hi>Princess</hi> more inflexible. Afterwards when Mr. <hi>Stewart</hi> by many repeated Letters pressed his Friend to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new his Importunities to the <hi>Pensioner</hi> for an Answer; He having also said in his <hi>Letters,</hi> that he writ by the <hi>King's Order</hi> and Direction; upon this the <hi>Pensioner</hi> having consulted the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Princess,</hi> drew his Letter first in <hi>Dutch,</hi> and communicated it to them, and it being approved by them, he turned it into <hi>Latin:</hi> but because it was to be shewed to the <hi>King,</hi> he thought it was fit to get it to be put in <hi>English,</hi> that so their <hi>Highnesses</hi> might see that Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his <hi>Letter,</hi> which was to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to His Majesty: and they having appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of it, he sent it with his own in <hi>Latin,</hi> and it was delivered to the <hi>King.</hi> This account was given me by my Friend, who added that it would appear ere long in a more Authentical manner: and by this I suppose the Impudence of those men does sufficiently appear who have the brow to publish such stuff, of the Falsehood of which they themselves are well assured: and therefore I may well conclude that My Lord Presidents <hi>Licence</hi> was granted by him, with that carelessness with which most Books are read and licensed. Our Author pretends, that he cannot believe that this <hi>Letter</hi> could flow from a <hi>Princess</hi> of <hi>so sweet a temper,</hi> page 62. and yet others find so much of the <hi>sweetness</hi> of her <hi>Temper</hi> in it, that for that very reason, they believe it the more easily to have come from her. No passion nor indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet zeal appears in it: and it expresses such an extended Charity and Nobleness of Temper, that these Characters shew it comes from one that has neither a narrowness of Soul, nor a fourness of Spirit. In short, she proposes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it, but to preserye that <hi>Religion,</hi> which She believes the <hi>true one:</hi> and that being secured, She is willing that all others enjoy all the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of Subjects,</hi> and the <hi>Freedoms of Christians.</hi> Here is <hi>Sweetness of Temper</hi> and <hi>Christian Charity</hi> in their fullest extent. The other Reason is so mysteriously expressed, that I will not wrong our Author by putting it in any other words than his own, Page 62. <hi>She is certainly as little pleased to promote any thing to the disturbance of a State, to which She still seems so nearly related.</hi> She <hi>seems still,</hi> are two significant words, and not set here for nothing. <hi>She seems</hi> (in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) only <hi>Related</hi> to the <hi>Crown;</hi> that is, She is not really so: but there is something that these Gentlemen have in reserve to blow up this <hi>seeming</hi> Relation. And She seems <hi>still,</hi> imports that tho this apparent Relation is suffered to pass at present, yet it must have its period: for this <hi>seems still</hi> can have no other meaning. But in what does She promote the <hi>disturbance of the State,</hi> or <hi>patronise the Opposers of her Parents?</hi> as he says afterwards, (ibid.) Did She Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously interpose in this matter, or was not her sense asked? And when it was asked, must She not give it according to her Conscience? She is too perfect a pattern in all other things, nor to know well how great a <hi>respect</hi> and <hi>submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> She owes her <hi>Father:</hi> but She is too good a Christian, not to know that her duty to God must go first: and therefore in matters of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> when her mind was asked, She could not avoid the giving it according to her Conscience, and all the invidious Expressions which he fastens on this <hi>Letter,</hi> and which he makes so many Arguments, to shew that it could not flow from her, are all the malicious and soon discovered Artifices, of one that knew that She had ordered the <hi>Letter,</hi> and that thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self safe in this disguise, in the discharging of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46081:5"/>his malice against her. So ingratefully is She requited by a party for whom She had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed so much Compassion and Charity. This Author, page 53 thinks, it is an <hi>Indecent fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cast to be always erecting such Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ams for the next Heir, both in Discourse and Writing, as seem almost to calculate the Nativity of the present:</hi> and he would almost make this <hi>High Treason.</hi> But if it is so, there were many <hi>Traitors</hi> in <hi>England</hi> a few years ago; in which the <hi>next Heir,</hi> tho but a <hi>Brother,</hi> was so much considered, that the <hi>King</hi> himself lookt as one out of countenance and abandoned; and could scarce find Company enough about him for his entertainment, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Bedchamber or in his Walks; when the whole Dependance was on the <hi>Successor:</hi> so if we by turns look a little at the <hi>Successor,</hi> those who did this in so scandalous a manner, ought not to take it so very ill from us. In a Melancholy State of things, it is hard to deny us, the consolation of hoping that we may see <hi>better Days.</hi> But since our Author is so much concerned, that this <hi>Letter</hi> should not be in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manner imputed to the <hi>Princess,</hi> it seems a little strange, that the <hi>Prince</hi> is so given up by him, that he is at no pains to clear him of the Imputation. For the happy Union that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, will readily make us conclude, that if the <hi>Prince</hi> ordered it, the <hi>Princess</hi> had likewise her Share in it. I find but one glance at the <hi>Prince</hi> in the whole Book, Page 52. when the Author is pleasing himself with the hopes of Protection from the <hi>Royal Heir</hi> out of a sense of <hi>Filial Duty:</hi> He concludes, <hi>Especially when so nearly allied to the very Bosom of a Prince whose way of worship neither is the same with the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal here, and in whose Countries all Religions have been ever alike tolerated.</hi> The Phrase of <hi>so near an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance to the very Bosom of a Prince,</hi> is somewhat extraordinary: An Author that will be florid, scorns so simple an Expression as <hi>married:</hi> he thought the other was more lotty. But the matter of this Period is more remarkable: it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Prince's</hi> way of Worship was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o different from ours: tho we hear that he goes frequently with the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rincess</hi> to her Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: and expresses no aversion to any of our Forms, tho he thinks it decent to be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly in the Exercises of Devotion that are authorised in <hi>Holland:</hi> and as for that, that <hi>all Religions have been ever alike tolerated there,</hi> it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of our Authors flights. I do not hear that t ere are either <hi>Bonzis</hi> or <hi>Bramans</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> or that the <hi>Mahometans</hi> have their <hi>Mosques</hi> there: And sure his Friends the <hi>Rom. Catholicks</hi> will tell him, that <hi>all Religions</hi> are not <hi>alike tolerated there.</hi> Thus I have followed him more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this Article, than in any other, it being that of the greatest Importance, by which he had endeavoured to blast all the good effects which the <hi>Pensioners Letter</hi> has had among us.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. I have now gone over that, which I thought most Important in this Paper: and in which it seemed necessary to inform the Publick aright, without insisting on the particular Slips of the Author of it, or of the Advantages that he gives to any that would answer him more particularly. I cannot think that any man in the Nation can be now so weak, as not to see what must needs be the effect of the Abolition of the <hi>Tests:</hi> after all that we see and hear, it is too great an Affront to Mankind to offer to make it out. A mans understanding may really mislead him so far as to make him change his <hi>Religion,</hi> he remaining still an <hi>honest Man:</hi> but no man can pretend to be thought an <hi>honest Man,</hi> that betrays the Legal, and now the only Visible Defences of that <hi>Religion</hi> which he professes. The taking away the <hi>Test</hi> for publick Employments, is to set up an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice at F. <hi>Peters</hi>'s for all Pretenders: and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a Pretender will not be so much as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, till he has first abjured: so that every Vacancy will probably make five or six Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites: and those <hi>Protestants</hi> who are already in Employments, will feel their ground quickly sail under them, and upon the first complaint, they will see what must be done to restore them to favour. And as for the two Houses of <hi>Parliament,</hi> as a great <hi>Creation</hi> will presently give them the Majority in the House of <hi>Lords:</hi> so a new set of <hi>Charters,</hi> and bold <hi>Returns,</hi> will in a little time give them likewise the Majority in the House of <hi>Commons:</hi> and if it is to be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed that <hi>Protestants,</hi> who have all the Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Law,</hi> for their <hi>Religion,</hi> can throw that up; who can so much as doubt that when they have brought themselves into so naked a condition, it will be no hard thing to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn their whole Establishment: and then, perhaps we shall be told more plainly, what is now but darkly insinuated to us, by this Author: that the Next Heir <hi>seems still to be so nearly related to this State.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46081:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>